Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, (7 boxes)
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints:, (192 items)
    - Paityn (with braid) and Kaitlyn (Katy, or Peanut) at their grandmother's, Betty Twedt, 801 West Avenue, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2005, 186
      Katy is looking out the window of what was once their grandfather's bedroom (Dave Twedt). Katy's 6th birthday.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt sharing a laugh with Reverend Ward Satterly, who is visiting from North Dakota during Spencer's 125th Anniversary celebration (we were in the Catholic Parish Center), July 18, 2005, 187
      The Reverend's wife was one of six deaths during the May 30, 1998 tornado... He married Kara and Danny Stone in September, 1998... A sign on the Parish Center's door advertised free lots to those who would build in Spencer.
    - Spencer, South Dakota celebrating 125 years of existence, June 18, 2005, 188
      The local firemen are competing with one another to see who can spray the barrel to the opposite end of the suspended rope.
    - Local celebrating the 125th anniversary of Spencer, South Dakota, June 18, 2005, 189
    - Danny Stone working on his lawn mower, Spencer, South Dakota, June 18, 2005--the 125th anniversary of Spencer, 190
    - Kaitlyn ("Peanut") at work in Dave and Mary Twedt's garden (her grandparents), Memorial Day Weekend, 2006 (8 years since the May 30, 1998 tornado), 191
      About 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota, the intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and McCook County Road 431.
    - Kaitlyn, holding her dance outfit, and her sister, Paityn, with their great-grandmother, Betty Twedt, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, June, 2006, 192
      (June Thompson and I lived 3 blocks away.)
    - Breyton, Paityn, Mary Twedt and Katie playing "hillbilly golf" in front of Dave and Mary's home south of Spencer, South Dakota, June, 2008, 193
      Hillbilly golf is a game played with two golf balls attached by a string of 18 inch rope. Each player has a set of three, and they toss them one at a time to one of two "gates" set about 20 feet apart. When a flopping string of golf balls catches a rung and stays on or wraps itself around, points are awarded: 3 points for the top, 2 for the middle, 1 for the bottom. The player who gets 21 points first wins.
    - Kaitlyn Ann Fredricks ("Peanut") rounding third base, Spencer, South Dakota, July 2, 2008, 194
    - Kaitlyn and Paityn in the swimming pool behind Dave and Mary Twedt's, the weekend before school started, August 16, 2008 (8x10 contact print), 195
      The pool had been part of the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. The building Dave and Mary made into a home following the Spencer tornado on May 30, 1998. Image made with a handbuilt 8x10 camera, fitted with a 100 year old lens.
    - Kaitlyn ("Peanut", center) and her friend Brooklin from Spencer (left) helping Mary Twedt prepare her Home and Garden Party Brochures. At Dave and Mary Twedt's home, corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, August 16, 2008, 196
      Mary has been hosting Home and Garden Parties in private homes, school fundraisers, etc, for a second income. 5x7 contact print from handmade, handheld camera.
    - Craig Leach (neighbor) and Jenna Webb behind her home in Spencer, South Dakota, August, 2008 (8x10 print), 197
    - Brandon Stone listening to the after-game speech given by his coach, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, August 23, 2008, 198
      His Junior League football team from Salem, South Dakota had just played their first competitive game of the season. The opposing, more experienced team won... Four years earlier, Brandon, his mother, Kara and his two younger sisters, Rebecca and Tiffany, were involved in a rollover accident about a mile from Spencer. He kicked out the window of the minivan and ran a 1/4 mile in stocking feet through the snow and ice to get help, essentially saving her life.
    - Suzy Webb being escorted down the aisle of St Mary's Catholic Church in Salem, South Dakota, by her mother, Nancy Webb, September 27, 2008, 199
      (Daughter, mother, Virgin Mary.)
    - Suzy Webb's wedding reception, the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, September 27, 2008, 200
      Her father, Lloyd Webb, is in the doorway. (Suzy was adopted by the Webb's when she was a child. Lloyd and Nancy had several foster children come and go from their home. Jenna--not pictured--was their only biological child.)
    - Alexa Roth (the daughter of Vicki, a foster child Lloyd and Nancy raised) by the water tank in the north pasture, 200 yards from the farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, September 29, 2008, 201
      We were taking a break between Suzy Webb's wedding and the reception to be held later that evening. This is the first time Nancy had seen Lloyd in two and a half years.
    - The enigmatic Lloyd Webb (Vicki and Nancy in the background, the north pasture), McCook County, South Dakota, September 27, 2008, 202
      I had not seen Lloyd in nearly four years--about the time he and Nancy divorced. When this image was made, he was living in Sheldon, Iowa, an hour and a half from Sioux Falls and working in an ethanol plant. I once thought of him as my closest friend in South Dakota... Many people thought the tornado had hardly fazed Lloyd, and they were probably correct. But nobody in his family called and asked how he was in the weeks that followed the storm... This image was made the day Suzy Webb married her high school boyfriend, Mike... Lloyd had not been out to the farm in nearly three years. It was hard to know what he was thinking.
    - Lloyd and Nancy Webb following the horses back to the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, September 27, 2008, 203
      Later that evening they will attend Suzy and Mike's wedding reception in Salem, ten miles east. Nancy's grandfather, Tillotson, homesteaded this land shortly before South Dakota became a state in 1889.
    - Nancy Webb returning one of her two doves to its cage, September, 2008, 204
      We were in the stairwell landing of the farmhouse, about an hour after Suzy Webb's wedding.
    - Most of Suzy Webb and Mike's wedding party, the National Guard Armory, Salem, South Dakota, September 27, 2008, 205
      From left to right: Jenna Webb and Craig; Nancy and Lloyd Webb; Alexa and DJ (Vicki's children); Mike and Suzy; Isaac (Jenna's son); Vicki and her husband; Derrick; and Myrta Wold, Nancy Webb's sister.
    - My god-daughter, Kaitlyn Ann Fredricks (Peanut), riding in the passenger seat of my 1993 Toyota Camry, heading west on 33rd Street, approaching Minnesota Avenue, on our way back to Grandma Betty's (Dave Twedt's mother) where Peanut spends the night on dance nights, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, September, 2008, 206
      (I've been taking Peanut to and from her dance lessons since she was five years old.)
  - 16x20 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints:, (14 items)
    - The doors to the National Guard Armory, Salem, South Dakota (10 miles East of Spencer), June 1998, 44 (Box 25)
    - A backhoe operator from California picking up rubble across from the grain elevator in Spencer, June 1998, 42
    - South Dakota Department of Corrections inmates working to clean up Spencer from the May 30, 1998 F-4 tornado, June 1998, 33
    - Rain, wipers on the windshield of my 1981 VW pickup, heading East on SD Highway 38 between Spencer and Salem, June, 1998, 34
    - Reverend Thomas Christopher standing on what is left at the Trinity Lutheran Church in Spencer, June 1998, 26
      Thomas (in center with horn) has momentarily borrowed the horn from the boy standing next to him. This was about an hour before a church service was held on this floor to celebrate the old church and to plan a new one on the same location. The banner reads: On Him Alone We Build.
    - Inside the fallen water tower in Spencer (from the May 30 tornado), June 1998, (unnumbered)
    - Bernie Opland (seated inside the skip loader) and a friend who came out for the day gathering tornado damaged vehicles to crush in Bernie's portable car crusher, June 1998, 210
      Close to 200 vehicles were crushed and hauled away by Bernie following the May 30 tornado.
    - Spencer, South Dakota's Cardinals -- the PeeWee League, July 2008, 209
      The kids Chatterley knows are Rebecca Stone (far left), Paityn Fredricks (fourth from left), Kaitlyn Fredricks (eighth from left), Breyton Fredricks (next to Kaitlyn, front). Chad Mentle is the coach (wearing sunglasses). This image was shot at Spencer's ballfield is in the Northeast part of town.
    - Standing in Dave and Mary Twedt's backyard area and looking toward Spencer on the 10 year anniversary of Spencer's tornado, May 2008., 208
      This photograph was made with Chatterley's hand-made camera fitted with a 100 mm lens removed from a plastic camera.
    - Men taking down a VFW flag in the back at a pickup truck following a parade to celebrate the 125th anniversary of Spencer, June 2005., 207
    - Riding with Lloyd Webb in the North pasture (3 miles North of Spencer), passing a frozen pond, March 1999, 121
    - Standing on the platform where the old Spencer water tower stood, facing Southeast, New Year's Day, 1999, 108
      The home in the center of the photograph belongs to Cookie Mentle. Her son Troy once owned the car in the driveway. Troy, Richard Stone, and another boy were fishing during the day of the May 30, 1998 tornado. They were in Troy's garage cleaning fish when Troy saw the tornado coming into town. He managed to get himself, Richard and the other boy into a storm cellar just seconds before the tornado passed over them. Richard Stone credits Troy for saving his life. Troy died the following Halloween weekend from liver failure due to excessive drinking. He was living an apartment in Sioux Falls, South Dakota. I spoke to him on the phone just a few days before. His name is present on the tornado memorial in town along with the six others who passed on May 30, 1998. The Stones' house is in the distance to the left.
    - Burning discarded buiding material and rubbish in front of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farm house, 3 miles north of Spencer, the day before Thanksgiving, 1998, 93
    - A few spot "test" fires that have been lit in the rubble following the razing of most of Spencer, June 1998, 54
      This is one of two large trenches dug to accept the tornado damaged town following the May 30, 1998 tornado, June 1998
  - Spencer, South Dakota Series, 11x14 gelatin silver work prints, untitled and undated, (62 prints) (Box 25)
- Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers, 2002 and undated, (1 box)
  Consists of one 11x14 print, two 6x20 prints, and eleven 16x20 prints, all selenium-toned gelatin silver prints. Founded in 1994, the Durham, North Carolina based Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers (TROSA) is a multi-year residential program that enables substance abusers to be productive, recovering individuals by providing comprehensive treatment, work-based vocational training, education, and continuing care. Chatterley's photographs document the program and its residents in the spring and summer of 2002. Original captions taken from back of prints. Arranged in original order as received.
  - 11x14 print of William Mack or "Mr. Mac." Head of the TROSA brick laying crew (staff) at his home in Durham, North Carolina, 2002 (Box 26)
  - 6x20 panorama print of New TROSA resident trying on clothes in the TROSA warehouse. Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring (3 negatives printed consecutively)
  - 6x20 panorama print of TROSA resident prior to graduation ceremony (2 year program). National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring
  - 16x20 print of the TROSA band during rehearsal. ("T-West") Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring
  - 16x20 print of TROSA staff and residents (Kevin McDonald, Director, is closest to camera). Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug.
  - 16x20 print of TROSA residents gathering before graduation ceremony. National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug.
  - 16x20 print of TROSA graduates. National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug.
  - 16x20 print of TROSA garage and donated cars to residents who are about to graduate from the program. "T-West" Durham, North Carolina, 2002
  - 16x20 print of Learning to make biscuits. T-North (TROSA) Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers, Durham, NC, 2002
  - 16x20 print of TROSA resident with One Year Medal-"T-North" Durham, North Carolina, undated
  - 16x20 print of TROSA moving crew at Duke University
  - 16x20 print of Mr. Mac
  - 16x20 print of TROSA kitchen staff
  - Untitled and undated 16x20 print of a group of workers sitting on a stoop
- Other Images, 2006-2007, (1 folder)
  Two prints that are not related to other series in this collection.
  - 6x20 print, Looking west, under the Mississippi River Bridge, Memphis, Tennessee. After a rare snowstorm. Holga plastic "panoramic" camera, 2006 Feb. (Box 27)
  - The godhead statue from behind (god the father, son, holy ghost). Salt Lake City, Utah, August 2007
    Photograph made with Chatterley's 1st handmade camera, a 5x7 aluminium camera painted red.
- Other Materials Series, 2004-2008, (1 box)
  Consists of a publication on Asian migrant communities in N.C. containing Chatterley's work on Cambodian Americans, and five audio cassette tapes with interviews of Chatterley discussing his career as a documentary photographer. The interviews have been digitized and stored on a library server; listening copies must be made for access. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use this material.
  - Lau, Barbara. From Cambodia to Greensboro: Tracing the Journeys of New North Carolinians. [Exhibit catalogue.] With contributions by Thomas A. Tweed and Sally Peterson, and photographs by Cedric N. Chatterley. Greensboro, NC: Greensboro Historical Museum, 2004. (Box 27)
    The Greensboro Historical Museum mounted an exhibition from December 2003 to December 2005 entitled From Cambodia to Greensboro: Tracing the Journeys of New North Carolinians. 2003 marked the twentieth anniversary of the Cambodian community in Greensboro, North Carolina, and the exhibition and book traced the community's growth and the experiences of its population.
  - Cassette tapes, 2008
    Five audiocassettes containing an interview with Chatterley describing his life and career as a documentary photographer. Titles transcribed from cassette labels.
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Digital files of these recordings are available, but listening copy must be made before contents can be accessed. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use these materials.]
    - Cedric, tape 1, 2008 Apr. 18
    - Cedric, tape 2, 2008 Apr. 18
    - Cedric, tape 1 of 2, 2008 Apr. 20
    - Lesley Williams/Cedric N. Chatterley, 2008 Apr. 22
    - Lesley Williams/Cedric N. Chatterley, 2008 Apr. 23